Hello, and welcome to another code walkthrough for Computer Architecture for Everybody.
In this walkthrough we're going to walk through the uppercase converter.
So what this is, is this is again WASM in the JavaScript environment, so it's output
is console.log and that's about it, we're not even taking some input, we're going to
hard code our input, and then what we're going to do is write a function called make an uppercase
copy of the string, okay, and so this gives us a little bit more time to take a bit more
look at WASM, not that I want you to understand or code WASM, you may even use AI to help
solve this one assignment, so you're going to take this uppercase code and you're going
to write a lowercase version of it, so you got to kind of dig through this code and figure
out where it's doing the uppercase, and then switch it to doing lowercase, and it might
be a little bit of work, and you might even use AI a little bit to help you do this, but
I'm just going to walk through this code to help you out.
Our output is going to go to console.log, we're going to create some memory, we're going
to put a string in there at location zero, and then we're going to make it so JavaScript
can execute it, and so we are going to then say copy and go to uppercase, and we're taking
some input variables, some making some local variables, so this parentheses func, it basically
WASM is a stack oriented language, so when you go into a func, you can think of a new
stack frame being created, just like you would in any other programming language, so in that
stack frame, there are variables that belong in that stack frame, and that's what we're
talking about here, and we're setting some values and getting things done, and then we
have some two instructions, or two instructions that might look a little weird to you, one
is the block, and so the idea, there are no labels in WASM, there are constructs, there
is an execution stack, and so when you start a block, and we'll go down to the bottom of
this block, where's the end of the block, I think the end of the block is right here,
oh wait, oh, I missed it, missed it, come back, come back, okay, I think the end of the block
is here, yeah, no, the end of the block is here, and this is the end of the loop, and
so what happens here is the block creates a temporary label that only exists in this
block, and you can branch to the loop end, it doesn't have to be named copy loop end,
they just named it copy loop end, because that's what's going on, so if this branch,
if true, this is doing a comparison between the character to see if it was a zero byte,
and if we hit the zero byte, we're going to exit the loop, and we're going to branch to this copy
end, now copy end is not the top of this, it is the next statement after the end of
the block, so when you say branch if copy loop end, you're exiting, so branches in WASM
are more about exiting where you're at and going to the next place, so that branch goes
to here, there is no label here, so if we were doing this in assembly language, we would
put a label here, and we would jump to the label, you're only allowed to jump out of
things or to the top of things, and so that's the way we exit it, so this is a loop that's
reading the data, and checking for a zero byte, and if we get a zero byte, we're done
with the loop, so that is the block, okay, block is something that can be exited, think
of it from a C perspective and a Python perspective, as this is like a break, it's a break out
of this block, BRF dollar copy loop end breaks out of the block that has the label dollar
copy loop end, so that is just a way to start a block and get out of the block, so that's
like a break statement, all of the looping in WASM is basically kind of like a while true
loop, both in Python and in C, it's like an infinite loop, and all we're doing with this
loop statement, it has no logic to it, it is defining another label, this label is only
accessible between the beginning and the end of the loop, so here is the end of the loop,
and we have, we're jumping to the top, if you don't have this BR dollar copy underscore
loop, it's not going to go back up, so the while loop is not automatic, you have to do something
at the bottom of the loop to go up, this is like a continue in either Python or C, so
continue the loop, go up to the top, now, there is no automatic incrementing, there
is no plus plus in here, no auto ion range of five, nothing, you have got to add one
to your, yeah, so we're going to add one to our counter, they're adding one to the counter
with this little for statement bit of code, for instruction piece of code, so they're
doing the plus plus as it were, or advancing the iterator, you have to do it in WAT, and
you're seeing quickly like, whoa, this is a pain, why isn't there just an increment
instruction, there isn't, there's an add one, you put the current value of I on the stack,
put the one on the stack, you add the top two items of the stack, and then you set it
back into the I variable, and then you go up to the top of the loop, so this is like
an infinite loop, and it goes until at the top, of course, it reads the offset piece
of the, it takes the, it takes, it doesn't even have an offset lookup, 6502 had an offset
lookup in it, and it says, give me the variable and add the I to it, it's why you have zero
based arrays, add it, and then load that, I don't know what this T does, but then we're
going to check to see if the character we just got is a zero, and then we're going to branch
out of the loop, and you know, then there are things like this dollar char, this is
a local variable, and then when we finally get done with this function, we are going
to return at the end of the function, and then that's going to kinda clear all that local
stuff off the stack, the stack frame, and then we're going to go, so if we got our main
function, and this main function is what is going to be called from the JavaScript, so we're
going to grab the string, we're going to grab its length, and we're going to call the copy and
uppercase routine, push some things in and call copy and uppercase, and then we're going
to print out the output of our function and the length, and then we're going to be done,
so, this is, oh I need to talk about if, I didn't talk about if, oh here we go, this
is the if, so this if looks okay, it's got an if then else, by the way, there is no elif,
you just have to keep nesting your elses, else, else, else, else, it's like going back
20 years, 30 years, okay, if, and then this, checking to see if it's greater, this is really,
this is a logic statement, we're grabbing the character, we're checking to see if it's
greater than a lowercase a, or, is it greater than lowercase a, and less than lowercase
c, less than or equal to, so it's doing a greater than or equal to, and a less than
or equal to, and this and is taking the two logic results that are sitting on the stack,
and then being true or false based on those two logic results popping it off, so it's
a stack oriented computation, and so if this resulted in a true, meaning it's greater than
or equal to a, and less than or equal to z, if it's true, we're going to convert that
character by subtracting 32, and then we're going to store it back in, and so that is
what we're going to do, well we're going to calculate the character, then we're going
to store it here, it's just really wordy, I mean a center language seems easier, now
the reality is most browsers don't execute this literally, it can, and it's still pretty
fast, you can execute this with an interpreter, and it runs plenty fine, but you can also
do what's called cross compiling it into native code, the key is that the way it's written,
a compiler can verify that this is not like doing naughty things, it's not like reading
memory doesn't belong to it, you can't jump to places that don't belong to you, you can't
execute code, there's so many things that stops you from doing, which is that sandboxing
thing, so we have gone through our loop, we've converted all the stuff to uppercase, left
the letters that are already uppercase alone, and then we print it all out, so with all
that, let's compile it and run it, so remember in this screen, the WAT is being assembled
inside the JavaScript, this is just a JavaScript button, the WAT is being assembled inside
the JavaScript, and then it is being executed inside the browser, and the results are coming
back to JavaScript, and that's it, so we got our uppercase, and your assignment is to adapt
this and adapt it so it does lowercase, it even tells you like, oh, it's a slightly different
number, maybe you want to do a different if, there you go, so it's not trying to make it
super hard for you, but you gotta dig through here, look enough, and you'll mess it up,
and then you just go reload the sample code, and then you fix it again until when you run
it, it says the correct output happens, so that this could all be lowercase, and then
you will have passed the autograder, let's go ahead and run the autograder on this, it's
going to fail, you gotta keep the original string, it compiled it, no, it didn't, we got the
wrong one, that's because I didn't change the code, so there you go, now that's your job,
you're going to fix that in the autograder, okay, so this is a little more detail in the walkthrough
where we build a function, we talk about the block, we talk about how break works, how
continue works, and then how if then, there is an else, but there is no else if, and we
talked about the stack and stack approach, you can talk a bunch to AI about this and
learn as much or as little as you want about WASM, I just wanted to expose you to WASM
because it is going to be increasingly important going forward when we talk about different
kinds of software systems, cheers.